Babbitt, Bill; Collection apap204
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Bill Babbitt Collection1970, 1982, 1991-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Babbitt, Bill
apap204
3.32 cubic ft.
The Bill Babbitt Collection documents nearly ten years of legal efforts to spare Manny Babbitt's life from execution, and two decades of advocacy activities to try to abolish the death penalty.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department Special Collections and Archives by Bill Babbitt in 2008.
Biographical Sketch
Bill Babbitt is an activist in the abolition movement. He regularly speaks out against the capital punishment system after promising his younger brother Manny he would campaign to end the death penalty. On May 4, 1999 Bill Babbitt witnessed fifty-year-old Manny Babbitt's execution by the State of California at San Quentin prison.
The sons of an ĂŠmigrĂŠ from the Cape Verde Islands off the coast of western Africa, Manny and Bill Babbitt grew up in a family of eight children in Wareham, Massachusetts. Enlisting in the Marines as a teenager, Manny Babbitt served two tours of duty in Vietnam, including fighting at the siege at Khe Sanh in 1968. He later received a Purple Heart for wounds sustained during his military service in 1998, while a prisoner on Death Row.
In the years following his discharge Manny Babbitt lived in Massachusetts and Rhode Island where he suffered from schizophrenia and post-traumatic stress disorder. According to Carbone, he spent time in psychiatric institutions, failed at relationships, lived periodically on the streets, drank and engaged in drug use, and went to prison for committing increasingly violent crimes. He moved in September 1980 to Sacramento, California to be with his brother Bill and sister-in-law Linda. There Manny Babbitt was ultimately tried and convicted of the murder of an elderly woman, Leah Schendel, who died of cardiac arrest after being severely beaten during a robbery in her home in December 1980.
After discovering his brother might be involved in this crime, Bill Babbitt approached the police and assisted them with the arrest of Manny Babbitt. Bill Babbitt states the authorities promised his brother would receive psychological help and placement in a mental health facility rather than on Death Row. In 1982, however, after being found sane and guilty of murder, Manny Babbitt was sentenced to death. According to Doyle, his family strongly believes that his initial lawyers were not competent nor did they offer post-traumatic stress disorder as part of the defense. While Manny Babbitt never denied committing the crime, he stated he could not remember anything about that night.
During the 1990s Manny Babbitt had a new legal defense team dedicated to trying to appeal his conviction, secure a new trial, and spare his life through legal channels. It was led by public defender and lead counsel Jessica McGuire and a fellow Vietnam veteran and trial attorney Chuck Patterson. In addition to Manny and Bill Babbitt's family and supporters, other Vietnam veterans also petitioned California Governor Gray Davis for clemency in this case. Both legal activity and media coverage of the case intensified in the early months of 1999, leading up to Governor Davis denying clemency, several high courts rejecting last minute appeals and intervention, and Manny Babbitt's subsequent execution.
Bill Babbitt continues to campaign against the death penalty and is frequently interviewed on network television news programs, radio stations, major daily newspapers, and magazines. He attends anti-death penalty rallies, testifies before state legislative committees, and often speaks alongside David Kaczynski, the executive director of New Yorkers Against the Death Penalty, before student and legal groups. David Kaczynski assisted federal authorities with the apprehension of his brother Ted Kaczynski, known as the "Unabomber." The documentaries And Then One Night: The Making of Dead Man Walking with Sister Helen Prejean and Mike Farrell and A Question of Justice, also with David Kaczynski, share the story of Bill and Manny Babbitt.
Bill Babbitt is active in several national organizations that oppose capital punishment. He was a board member of Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation from 2000-2004 and is a founding board member of Murder Victims' Families for Human Rights, where he still serves today.
Scope and Contents
The Bill Babbitt Collection documents nearly ten years of legal efforts to spare Manny Babbitt's life from execution, and two decades of advocacy activities to try to abolish the death penalty. The bulk of materials are court records from the 1990s related to Manny Babbitt's case. In addition, the collection includes the contents of Manny Babbitt's cell at San Quentin at the time of his execution, correspondence from both Manny and Bill Babbitt, speeches, prison records, materials from death penalty abolitionist organizations and conferences, and news articles about the case and Bill Babbitt's ongoing advocacy work.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
This series includes documents related to Bill Babbitt's campaign to end the death penalty. Correspondence, speeches, documents from the organizations Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation and Murder Victims' Families for Human Rights, pamphlets from various conferences, background information and data on capital punishment, and a printed tribute to Manny Babbitt comprise this series. There also are numerous news articles about Manny and Bill Babbitt spanning the years 1998 through 2008.
Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Capital punishment--United States; California Supreme Court; Babbitt, Manny; Sacramento County (Calif.); Legal documents; Aerogrammes; Administrative records; Newsletters
- Legal Materials, 1991-1999; 1; 1.82 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The majority of this series consists of court records from Manny Babbitt's case. There are materials from the District Court for the Eastern District of California, Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, California Supreme Court, and U.S. Supreme Court. The series also contains other legal documents, such as Manny Babbitt's last will and testament, and legal correspondence.
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1)
  - Legal Correspondence, 1991-1999 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 2)
  - California Supreme Court, Petition for writ of Habeas Corpus, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 3)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 4)
  - Supreme Court- Reply to Informal Response, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 5)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 6-9)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California request to expand. Exhibits: Vol. I, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 2-3)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California Exhibits: Vol. II, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 4-6)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California Exhibits: Vol. III, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 7)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California Exhibits: Vol. III, 1996 (Box 3 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1996 (Box 3 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 2-4)
  - District Court, 1997 (Box 3 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 5)
  - District Court: Vol. I of Appendix to motion to Amend findings, 1997 (Box 3 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 6-8)
  - District Court: Vol. II of Appendix to motion to Amend findings, 1997 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1-2)
  - District Court: Vol. III of Appendix to motion to Amend findings, 1997 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 3)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1997 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 4)
  - Court of appeals for the 9th Circuit, 1997-1998 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 5)
  - Court of appeals for the 9th Circuit- Source Material, 1997 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 6-7)
  - District Court for the Eastern District of California, 1998 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 8)
  - U.S. Court of appeals for the 9th Circuit, 1998-1999 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 9)
  - U.S. Supreme Court- Petition for Writ of Certiorari, 1998 (Box 4 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 10)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1)
  - Superior Court of California, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 2)
  - Choice of Execution method form, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 3)
  - Incomplete Petition for Clemency, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 4)
  - Supreme Court: Exhibits to Petition for Clemency. Vol. I, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 5-7)
  - Supreme Count: Exhibits to Petition for Clemency. Vol. II, 1999 (Box 5 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 8-10)
  - Reply to Response to Clemency Petition, 1999 (Box 6 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 1)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1999 (Box 6 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 2)
  - California Supreme Court, Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus and Emergency Application for stay of Execution, 1999 (Box 6 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 3)
  - California Supreme Court, Exhibits to Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus and Emergency Application for stay of Execution, 1999 (Box 6 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 4-5)
  - Death Certificate, 1999 (Box 6 (1-Legal Materials), Folder 6)
- Manny Babbitt, 1970-1999; Undated; 2; 0.67 cubic ft.
  The series contains the contents of Manny Babbitt's cell at the time of his execution in May 1999 and his original works, including several poems. There also is an empty cardboard box which housed Manny Babbitt's personal items in his cell. Please note that the dates for the series are not inclusive and the bulk of files date from the 1990s.
  - Dishcharge Report, 1970 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 1)
  - Publications, 1982-1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 2)
  - The Battle of Khe Sanh, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 3)
  - Legal Correspondence, 1991-1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1992-1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 5)
  - Khe Sanh Veterans Reunion, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from State of California or San Quentin, 1996-1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 7)
  - Copy of Purple Heart Award Certificate, 1998 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 8)
  - Book excerpts, Poems and Drawings, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 9)
  - Inmate Work Supervisors Time Log, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 10)
  - Petition for Clemency, 1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 11)
  - Exhibits to Petition for Clemency Vol. II, 1999 (Box 1 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 12-13)
  - Exhibits to Petition for Clemency Vol. II, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 1)
  - Reply to Response to Clemency Petition, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 2)
  - Property Inventory, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, Undated (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 5)
  - The Heart of Understanding, Undated (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 6)
  - Stamps, Undated (Box 2 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 7)
  - Valley of Decision, 1991 (Box 3 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 1)
  - Empty cardboard box which housed Manny Babbitt's personal items in his cell at San Quentin, Undated (Box 4 (2-Manny Babbitt), Folder 1)
- Advocacy, 1995-2008; Undated; 3; 0.83 cubic ft.
  This series includes documents related to Bill Babbitt's campaign to end the death penalty. Correspondence, speeches, documents from the organizations Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation and Murder Victims' Families for Human Rights, pamphlets from various conferences, background information and data on capital punishment, and a printed tribute to Manny Babbitt comprise this series. There also are numerous news articles about Manny and Bill Babbitt spanning the years 1998 through 2008.
  - Death Penalty Facts, 1995; 2000; 2005 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 1)
  - Bill and Linda Babbitt Correspondence, 1995; 1999-2006 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1996; 2001; 2006; Undated (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 3)
  - Letters Written by Manuel Babbitt to Bill and Linda Babbitt, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 4)
  - Manny Babbitt Articles, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 5)
  - Declaration of William Babbitt May, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 6)
  - Tribute to Manny Babbitt (unbound copy), 1999 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 7)
  - Tribute to Manny Babbitt (bound copy), 1999 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 8)
  - Manny Babbitt Articles, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 9-10)
  - Letters to Governor Davis and Mayor Brown, 1999; Undated (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 11)
  - Religious Views, 1999; Undated (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 12)
  - News Articles about Death Penalty, 1999-2001; 2005-2007 (Box 1 (3-Advocacy), Folder 13)
  - Advocacy Newsletters, 1999-2008 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 1)
  - Conferences and Events, 1999-2005 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 2)
  - Manny Babbitt Loaves and Fishes Donations, 2000 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 3)
  - Manuel Babbitt Information Sheets, 2000; Undated (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 4)
  - Murder Victims Families for Reconciliation, 2000-2003; Undated (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 5)
  - Bill and Manny Babbitt Media Coverage, 2000-2008 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 6)
  - California Death Row Inmates, 2002 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 7)
  - Campaign for the Nobel Peace Prize for Governor Ryan of Illinois, 2003 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 8)
  - Understanding Capital Punishment, 2003 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 9)
  - Capital Defense Handbook, 2005 (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 10)
  - Murder Victims' Families for Human Rights (MVFHR), 2005-2007; Undated (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 11)
  - Conferences and Events, 2006-2008; Undated (Box 2 (3-Advocacy), Folder 12)
  - Advocacy Magazines, 2007 (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 1)
  - Bill and Linda Babbitt Correspondence, 2007-2008; Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 2)
  - Visitor Passes, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 3)
  - Buttons, Stickers and Bumper Stickers, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 4)
  - Campaign to End the Death Penalty, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 6)
  - Advocacy Pamphlets and Backgrounders, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 7)
  - Bill Babbitt Remarks, Undated (Box 3 (3-Advocacy), Folder 8)